Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today we're
going to be learning about how to
prepare for the chemistry 3A ACS final,
which is for introductory chemistry.
So first off, congratulations for
making it to the very, very end of
your introductory chemistry course,
and you're ready to prepare for
the final stretch of the semester,
which is studying for your exam.
So with this series of videos, what
the entire point is, is that I'm going
to try to do my best to prepare you
for that exam so that way you can do
the best that's possible for you and
your abilities for what you've learned
across the course of the semester.
So what this whole thing is going to be
about is that this is going to be a series
of videos, which is going to focus on
how to break down ACS style questions.
And Specifically focusing on introductory
chemistry, which is our Chem 3A
course right here at our school.
So what these will mainly be is based
on the fundamentals of chemistry,
but this is a lot of these different
questions that we're going to go
over can be applied to Chemistry 1 or
Chemistry 1A, Chemistry 110 at different
schools, they can apply to them as well.
So in this particular video, we're going
to go specifically on what to expect
when you walk in on your final exam date.
What the format is and what you
should do to study and prepare for
it in the followup videos to come,
they will be more on individual
tests that are tailored to replicate.
Uh, A.
C.
S.
Tests.
So that way, you know exactly what
to expect and how to study for them
and how I kind of go through the
process of trying to play the game
that is known as a standardized exam.
So let's take a look.
Let's try to learn and try to do
our best on these on this exam.
And once again, well, congrats
on making it to the end.
Let's finish strong as we move forward.
So the first thing is, is that this,
what your final is, it's the standardized
exam, which is written by the American
Chemical Society, also known as the ACS.
Now what this exam is for is to
evaluate students on a national scale.
So your exam score is going to be
compared to those from people all
across the country in all kinds
of different areas of the country.
Now, what this test is used for, for
our class we're going to be focusing
on the general organic and biochemistry
type of exam, which is known as our
Chem 3A and then our Chem 3B course.
So you're going to be just doing
the general portion of it, so you're
going to be doing that subtest.
Now for anyone that is a chemistry
or a biology or an engineering major
that has to move forward into other
courses, you're gonna see this type
of exam again in gen Chem one and
and organic one and two as well.
Now, what this whole idea is for us
doing this is the one is to evaluate your
knowledge so that way we can see where
do you stand up to other students coming
from the same background as you and it.
One thing that we do with that
information is we use it to
try to improve our courses.
And to improve our program, right?
So that's one of the ideas behind a
lot of those results is actually kind
of what helps spawn one of the things
that helps spawn this YouTube channel.
Was because I wanted to find new
ways to help my students to try
to succeed into the next level.
So this is all to prepare
you for that next step.
So, you know, how to do standardized
testing, um, especially for all the, my
nerd, many of my future nurses out there.
Many of you will have
to take the T's exam.
Which does have standardized
chemistry, biology, mathematics,
questions on that test.
So you need to be able to know how
to critically evaluate and think your
way through those type of questions.
So when it comes to this, what
we're going to be doing is
the general chemistry subtest.
So the portion of this that you're
going to be taking is 60 questions
that has to be completed in 55 minutes.
What you're probably saying
to yourself, is he for real?
That is insane.
And the thing is, you've probably
heard a lot of your professors
have said this recently.
Whether it's me, or if you're in another
class watching this, that is a lot.
So what you're going to have to learn is
not only your chemistry knowledge, but
different strategies to make it easier.
The thing is with standardized tests,
a lot of them are actually doable with
Whether or not you really know the
entire concept, it's about being a good
test taker, not only a good chemist.
So when we're looking at this, now
the good thing is, is that this
entire test is all multiple choice.
And the thing is, it is designed to be
solvable, every question is designed
to be solvable in less than a minute.
So it's meant to be fast.
So when we break down this test, you're
going to see that about half the questions
are going to be calculation based.
Meaning that you're going to need to
use your calculator to solve them, or
it might be something that you can kind
of get the answer with, without even
looking at using your calculator, or
it's going to be a theory based question.
So something that has to do with
the conceptual understanding.
Now the thing about this is you cannot
use a programmable calculator on the
test, meaning that if you're someone
who has like a TI 83 or like a TI 84.
You can't use them, but you are welcome
to use your TI 36 calculator, which
is kind of what we always go through
and how we actually work this exam.
This is allowed because you
can't program it and put any
function that you want in it.
So keep that in mind.
If you are someone that has
a fancy calculator, you're
going to have to switch it out.
So if you need to do that, make sure you
talk to your instructor prior to the exam,
tell them that you need to switch it out.
Usually they're kept in every one of
the classrooms in the science building.
But to ensure that you do have
one, definitely make sure you ask.
Now, every instructor is a little
bit different on how they actually
enforce this one, but I would recommend
making sure you clarify that you
can use your calculator on the test.
If you're not sure, ask.
Um, if it's a Casio calculator,
usually you're fine.
Um, it's all the T, the high number TI
calculators that you got to watch out for.
The other thing you got to do when you
come to that day on the exam, Phones and
bags, they all need to be placed in the
front of the classroom out of the way.
Usually your teacher will have
a place where these can go.
Now when it comes to taking out an
exam, this is a standardized test.
It's not like a normal exam.
The instructor is responsible for
making sure that it's kept behind
locked doors and that essentially
none of that information escapes.
So one thing that you will have to do is
you need to have an ID or a phone or a
wallet ready to go that can be used as
collateral to exchange for that test.
So if, um, when you're given your
test booklet, you'll just give them,
you know, let's say your ID and
they'll hold onto it for the test
period and you get it back at the end.
Pretty, it's a pretty
easy exchange process.
Um, whenever you take your test,
you're always given a piece
of scrap paper to go with it.
Usually you're given two to three
pieces, so that way you have them ready.
Um, and now the whole reason is because
you cannot write in the exam book.
So, you're given scrap paper to
write anything you want on them, and
that's also the reason why you give
your ID as well, to double check
that, hey, you did not write in
this thing when you were given it.
So, when you show up, make sure
you have the right calculator,
don't write in the book, and you
can write all over the scrap paper.
Um, you will need a
scantron to do this test.
So for everybody, you
need a scantron 95677.
When you take this test, this type of
test, it's most likely the same scantron
you've been taking using all semester.
If you've been doing other, uh,
in person, regular scantrons,
it's most likely the same one.
Make sure you double check with your
instructor that is the same one for
me, you know, you can check my exam
review guides, but for other ones,
you know, make sure you check their
exam review, but generally we all use
the Scantron 95677 for Chem 3A exams.
Okay, let's take a look at the next.
So now that you're about to
take the exam, what is provided
for you to be able to take it?
The thing is that the scariest part is
up until this point you've been given
a ton of reference material in order to
succeed on your regular semester exams.
You might have been given a note
card, you might have been given
a periodic table, you might have
been given the yellow reference
sheet, maybe your solubility chart.
On the final, you don't get any of that.
The only thing you can have is
essentially what is given to you, which
one of them is the periodic table.
Now I copied an exact version of that
periodic table from this ACS test.
If you want to use this as a
template, feel free to do that.
This is something that I will
include in my study resources.
And if you want to message me,
I can give you a copy of it.
But is it is a bare bones periodic
table, meaning that notice if you kind
of zoom out on any of these elements.
They only have the following
piece of information.
They only have the atomic symbol or the
elemental symbol in all these, right?
So we have the symbol, we have the atomic
number, and then we have the atomic mass.
And that is all you are given for
any of these different species.
You have no electronegativity values.
You have no charges.
You are given basic pieces
of information, right?
So as you're kind of going through these,
you got to kind of remember what all these
different pieces of information, what
they all represent when you are kind of
writing your different symbols and how to
actually read them for how to calculate
your protons, electrons, neutrons.
Um, same thing with your
number of valence electrons.
So notice as well that it has
the old school archaic of 1, 2,
1a, 2a, 3a, 4a, 5a, uh, groups.
So one little trick about this is those
represent the number of valence electrons
that are for any of your species.
That is something I would
recommend writing down because I
can guarantee you there will be a
question about valence electrons.
And you have to be able to read that
old school periodic table to do that.
Um, you can also help use it for
your charges to, um, remember if
you, the total number of valence
electrons is always eight.
So if you just do eight minus
that, that group number, you
will get, uh, what the charges.
So if you think like eight minus
eight, that's zero, um, eight
minus, or seven minus eight would
be negative one, six minus eight
would be negative two, five minus.
Eight would be negative three, and that
can give you a lot of your charges too.
So make sure you practice
using a simple periodic table.
Other things that you're given is
you're given a very, very simple
list of abbreviations and symbols.
Sorry that this is a little skewed,
but this is something that is
coming out of an old exam and the
scan did not come out so great.
So the only thing that it gives you
is it tells you, well, okay, well,
what does every symbol mean in case
maybe you don't remember what it is?
Okay.
So I would get a little familiar with
some of the different symbols, right?
Know what a mole is, molarity,
molar, those different terminology.
The two conversions it does give you,
which are a little hidden is kilo, which
it tells you it's 10 to the three, right?
So one kilogram, for example,
is 10 to the three grams.
And then it also tells you
milli, which is on here as well.
So what that means is that,
uh, 10 to the negative three.
Um, grams is equal to one, or sorry,
when I say 10 to negative three grams,
is that one gram is equal to 1000
milligrams or 10 to negative three,
uh, going the other way as well.
So it gives you those types of
conversions, which sometimes the
helpful, but by this point in the class,
you should already know them, right?
So it doesn't give you much.
It also gives you the R constant,
which if it, if there's a constant
you need, it's always given to you.
So if you do see a constant, then maybe
it might, might let you know what that is.
It also tells you like, if there are any
weird notation, like grams per mole, you
notice the negative is letting you know,
Hey, it's, this is in, um, a fraction.
So there's not much.
Now, the other thing is, there's
no formulas that are given to
you on this test Either, and you
might be like, hold up, what,
like, this is already impossible.
So the first thing is, is you
can't give up on this test, right?
One of the things about it is for many
of you, this might be the kind of the
make it or break it point when it comes
to either passing or maybe getting the
grade that you really do deserve because
you've been working your butt off all
semester to either get an A or B or C
or whatever grade you, you, you deserve.
It is something you can't give up now.
The good news is there's not many
formulas you need, and I put together
the list of exactly what formulas
you do need for the final exam.
So the first thing is a lot of these
are the fundamentals, they're things
that you did in your lab practical,
they're things you've been using all
semester in different labs a lot.
The first one is, is your density, right?
Knowing your density is
grams per milliliter.
That is one of the most
core fundamental concepts.
You've been using it in probably three
or four different labs and you know it.
Molar mass, right?
Grams over moles.
You've had to use that since chapter
five and it's now chapter 14.
That's a, that's about
three months of using it.
There's also the following as well.
You have the dilution formulas
and knowing when to dilute
something, knowing molarity.
knowing your temperature conversions,
knowing the heat equation, which is Q is
equal to the FPM cat equation, Q is equal
to MC delta T, and then your gas laws.
Luckily, it's mainly comes down
to these two, which is the ideal
gas law in the combined gas law.
And we'll talk about when each one of
them is applied as we go through our
chapter analysis of what you need to
know exactly in order to ace this test.
Um, I also placed Dalton's law
here as well because it is a good
thing to understand the, either
the part, the mole and pressure
ratios that come along with it too.
So this is all of the formulas
that you do need to know.
So if you can memorize this list,
you will do just fine on knowing
any of the different calculations,
but that's not everything, right?
Stoichiometry is a big part too, so
you need to be able to do simple types
of calculations with that as well.
The next thing that we're going to do
is we're going to be going through the
exact step by step process and going
through every chapter that was covered
in Chem 3A, and we'll talk about exactly
what topics you need to study to,
in order to answer everything on the
upcoming test that you will be taking.
This is a general list.
This is something that's gone
over, going over multiple
different generations of this test.
So that way you know exactly what you need
to know to study for your test, what's
expected for you to know at this point.
So when you're doing this, the other thing
to keep in mind is all these questions
are something that's doable in a minute.
So they are short questions.
So you're not going to have to do some
crazy 30 step long problem that takes
you from a solution to a gas back to
mass with limiting reagents and balancing
and doing all these different steps.
They're mainly one to two step
problems that are quicker to do.
Before we go into the next
part, let's talk about some
more things as before that.
The first thing is what comes up, what
about, what else do you have to memorize?
I would recommend memorizing your
normal polyatomics, which is mainly
the ones with the eight endings.
The most common are
nitrate, carbonate, sulfate.
I would memorize their charges and what
they look like, and then hydroxide being
that's a part of almost every single base.
Okay.
Thanks.
So these are your most common
polyatomics that will be used.
The other thing that can be
helpful as well is memorizing
what an acid looks like, right?
An acid starts with an H, and
then a base ends in a hydroxide.
So knowing acids and bases, if
you know your strong acids and
bases, you will do just fine.
But if you want to add that to
the list as well, things to put
on a flashcard for yourself, it
will help you be able to study.
Let's look at how this
exam is going to be graded.
Now, for the next part of how it's going
to be graded, this is something that
tells you the honest truth of really
what happens behind the scenes when it
comes to your faculty grading this exam.
So with this, it is based off
the national average of the exam,
which is what's generally used to
determine whether or not you pass.
Usually what we do is, it's ultimately
always up to your professor.
They have the academic right to be able
to decide what your final grade is.
But generally what is used is
depends on what the average is.
The average is usually used to determine
what is generally a mid C grade.
So let's say if the average is 30
points, so right in the middle.
That's usually determined to
say, that's average, right?
So that's around, let's say, a 75%.
So usually what I always tell my
students to do is try to shoot
for half of them correctly.
Now when you're doing this exam,
it is not like a normal exam.
You are not supposed to
get 100 percent correct.
Generally, when we are grading
this, if you get probably above,
usually it's are about over 50
questions correct out of 60 of them.
This is generally considered
an A grade on the exam.
So the goal is not to get
100%, but the answer as many
as you can correctly, right?
So go through all of them,
answering what you know first.
It's about scoring points.
It's like a game that you're playing.
It's all about like, what is
the standard in this case?
Right.
It's all about, can I try to
get onto the right hand side?
of this bell curve when
we are scoring, right?
So if you can get more and more
points by answering what you do know,
it can help try to solidify your
grade into that better category.
If you end up like looking at
it and essentially just turning
off and be like, Oh, there's no
way I'm pretty much failed this.
That's not going to help you.
It's not going to help anything.
It's just going to put
you into the bad category.
So when you're taking it, if you don't
know something, yes, and move on.
You can always come back to it later.
If there's time being that you have
55 minutes, you have to answer as
many things quickly as you can.
And a lot of the problems
are really quick.
They don't even involve math.
So if you know your fundamentals and
your basics, then you should be fine.
So if you don't know it,
move on and just guess.
It's advantageous, meaning
it's in your benefit to answer
as many things as possible.
Because you're not deducted
for answering more questions.
You're only deducted if you
essentially don't put anything, right?
So you need to put as much as you can.
And the good thing is when you're
answering a lot of these questions, you
can eliminate usually one or two choices
because the numbers are completely
outside the realm of possibility.
They're not even close to
where they're supposed to be.
It's concepts that don't exist
when it comes to a theory.
They're names you've never seen before.
So, you can eliminate choices,
take educated guesses.
You've been taking a chem
course now for, for 18 weeks.
You can succeed and do this.
You just gotta believe in yourself
just like how I believe in you.
It's something that's entirely possible.
Do the best that you can while
you're going to go through it.
So keep that in mind while
you're, while you're trying to
understand all these questions.
Now, let's go through chapter by
chapter of what was covered in
this class throughout the different
weeks of what you need to study
in order to review your knowledge.
Now, keep in mind, a lot of
these different topics that we're
going to cover, you might have
forgotten a lot of them, right?
You've been lately probably been
focusing on balancing chemical reactions,
stoichiometry, and acids and bases, the
insanely hard topics, but you probably
forgotten that in the past you did some
easy things too, which were maybe just
counting protons, neutrons, electrons.
Trying to just figure out some
little geometry things, the
more simple counting things.
Now you gotta make sure you remember
them so you can get those points and
ensure you get the easier questions.
So that was the end of
part one of this video.
Being that it was going a little long,
I decided to cut it into two pieces.
So at the end of part one, we
went through the entire exam
and exactly what to expect.
In the follow up part, we're
gonna go through the exact chapter
by chapter synopsis of what to
study for that part of the exam.
If you'd like to, I did link in the
Chem 3A section of my channel, all the
different chapters which are covered.
So I have played up.
Essentially, if you go onto the homepage,
you look at the playlist, you'll see that
I have organized by chapter this course.
So you can go through and watch any
video on any topic that we cover
in that video to help you better
master every, every single thing.
Now, keep in mind, watching videos
is fantastic, but the real practice
comes from you doing the problems.
So when we're going through the
different parts of this review series,
I recommend trying to pause it, try to
do the problem on your own, and then
you can watch the video to be able to
see like what the actual questions are.
But thank you for listening.
I really appreciate you for doing this.
Hopefully it helps you study and
to do really well on your prep, on
your final and let me know if you
do need any help as we start to
go through this journey together.
Alright, let's take a look and
I'll see you guys all in the
future videos and thank you so
much for listening and watching.
Alright, I'll see y'all later, bye now!